The Gathering Storm is a drama, history film directed by Richard Loncraine.
A love story offering an intimate look inside the marriage of Winston and Clementine Churchill
during a particularly troubled, though little-known, moment in their lives.
Winston Churchill, played by Albert Finney.
Clemmie Churchill, played by Vanessa Redgrave.
Desmond Morton, played by Jim Broadbent.
Ralph Wigram, played by Linus Roache.
Ava Wigram, played by Lena Headey.
Sir Robert Vansittart, played by Tom Wilkinson.
The Gathering Storm is a BBC–HBO co-produced television biographical film
about Winston Churchill in the years just prior to World War II.
The title of the film is that of the first volume of Churchill's largely autobiographical six-volume history of the war,
which covered the period from 1919 to 3 September 1939, the day he became First Lord of the Admiralty.
The film, directed by Richard Loncraine and written by Larry Ramin and Hugh Whitemore, stars Albert
Finney as Churchill and Vanessa Redgrave as his wife Clementine Churchill ("Clemmie").
The film also features a supporting cast of British actors such as Derek Jacobi, Ronnie Barker (his first role since retiring in 1988), Jim
Broadbent, Tom Wilkinson, Celia Imrie, Linus Roache and Hugh Bonneville, and is notable for an early appearance by a young Tom Hiddleston.
Lena Headey, Simon Williams, and Edward Hardwicke all make
brief appearances amongst the supporting cast.
Among the film's executive producers were Ridley Scott and Tony Scott.
Originally the film was named The Lonely War.
Finney gained many accolades for his performance, winning both a BAFTA
Award for Best Actor and an Emmy for Outstanding Lead Actor.
Ramin and Whitemore won the Emmy for Outstanding Writing.
It won a Peabody Award in 2002 for being "a portrait of a 20th Century hero’s return from political obscurity to direct the destiny
of a nation." In 2016, Mark Lawson of The Guardian ranked it as the most memorable television portrayal of Churchill.
A 2009 sequel, Into the Storm, with Churchill portrayed by Brendan Gleeson,
focuses on the prime minister's days in office during World War II.
The film explores themes of world war ii, biography, based on true
story, british prime minister, british history.
The tone is emotional.